A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Knowledge, Creativity and Freedom, Media, Arts, and Culture, Media Unit, Office Files of Becky Lentz FA1426
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Knowledge, Creativity and Freedom, Media, Arts, and Culture, Media Unit, Office Files of Becky Lentz
1998-2007
Rockefeller Archive Center
Lentz, Becky (Roberta G.)
Ford Foundation
FA1426
8 Cubic Feet 21 document containers
Scope and Contents
This collection contains office files of Becky Lentz, who held positions as a Program Officer of Media, Arts, and Culture and a Program Officer for Electronic Media Policy. Materials include grant records, grant-funded materials, Requests for Grant Action (RGA), proposals, grant status reports, books, newsletters, working drafts, memos, publications, and correspondence.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically in two series:
1. Grant Files, 1998-2007
2. Conference Materials and Publications, 2000-2007
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation was chartered by Henry and Edsel Ford in 1936 "to receive and administer funds for scientific, educational and charitable purposes, all for the public welfare", and initially served the Ford family's charitable interests in the Detroit area. Following the deaths of Edsel Ford (1943) and Henry Ford (1947), the Foundation was propelled to the forefront of philanthropy as the largest American foundation in terms of both endowment and yearly expenditures, and with an international scope to its major program areas.
During the Foundation's first twenty years its major programs were in international economic development, primary and higher education, educational and public broadcasting, behavioral sciences, civil liberties, urban development, fine arts and the humanities. The Ford Foundation also partnered with the Rockefeller Foundation in supporting agricultural development in South America, Africa, and Southeast Asia. Since the 1970s, the Foundation has also pioneered programs in women's rights, energy policy, micro-financing in under-developed countries, establishing human rights groups, and improving international HIV/AIDS education.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This material was transferred to RAC in 2018 by the Ford Foundation and ingested by RAC as Accession 2018:040.
Communications; Media; Ford Foundation
- Grant Files, 1998-2007; 1
  - ACLU Foundation, 2000-2002 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Grant No.: 10150152
  - American Library Association, 2000-2001 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Grant No.: 10000970
  - American Library Association, 2001-2003 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bay Area Video Coalition, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Playback: A Preservation Primer for Video
  - Benton Foundation, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Publication - What's Going on in Community Media
  - Board of Global Ministries of the United Methodist Church, 2000-2001 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Grant No.: 10051071
  - Center for Democracy and Technology, 2003-2005 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Center for Digital Democracy, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Center for International Media Action, 2003-2004 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Grant No.: 10350692
  - Center for Media Education, 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Grant No.: 09901180
  - Center for Media Education (1 of 2), 2001 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Grant No.: 10100436
  - Center for Media Education (2 of 2), 2002 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Grant No. 10100436
  - Center for Policy Alternatives, 2000-2002 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Grant No.: 10100408 - includes newsletters, correspondence, and grant forms
  - Center for Public Integrity, 2005-2006 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Includes publication - Networks of Influence: The Political Power of the Communications Industry (2005) as well as a pamphlet and memos
  - City University of New York, 2001-2003 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Grant No.: 10250381 - includes memos, grant information, and report - Mapping Social Entrepreneurship and the Role of Charitable Foundations in Electronic Media: 1946-1996 (March 31, 2003)
  - Consumer Federation of America (1 of 2), 2004 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    Grant No.: 10350626 - grant report
  - Consumer Federation of America (2 of 2), 2004 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    Attachment #7 - Report - Abracadabra! Hocus-Pocus!: Making Media Market Power Disappear with the FCC's Diversity Index, Dr. Mark Cooper
  - Consumers Union, 1992-2005 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    Reports - The Digital Divide: Confronts the Telecommunications Act of 1996, Economic Reality vs. Public Policy (February 1999) and Electronic Waste: Finding Sustainable Solutions that Work Better for Consumers: A Consumers Union White Paper, Carolyn Cairns
  - Digital Media Forum - Leslie Harris and Associates, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    Report - Can the Information Commons Be Saved?: How Intellectual Property Policies Are Eroding Democratic Culture -- and Some Strategies for Asserting the Public Interest
  - Digital Media Forum - Leslie Harris and Associates, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    Includes Digital Media Forum - Annual Report (2001) and Ford Foundation Digital Media Forum, May 29-30, 2001 Alexandria, Virginia report
  - Digital Media Forum - Leslie Harris and Associates, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    Grant No.: 10100244 - Appendix A - Rapporteur's Report, Ford Foundation Digital Media Forum Retreat, May 30-31, 2001 Appendix B - Who Benefits Whom in Local Television Markets?, Joel Waldfogel; Appendix C - Privacy, Consumers, and Cost; Appendix D - Framing a Campaign to Defend the "Dot-Commons": Revised Proposal for a Program of Research and Advocacy, memos, drafts of reports, and correspondence
  - Digital Media Forum - Leslie Harris and Associates, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    Grant No.: 10100244 - Correspondence and Grant Status Report February 2002, Memos, and report - Bringing a Nation Online: The Importance of Federal Leadership
  - Duke Law School (1 of 3), 2002 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    Grant No.: 10100243 - Duke University School of Law, Ford Foundation Final Report: Public Interest for the Public Domain; Duke Law School Fellowship Program in Intellectual Property and the Public Domain, Ford Year-End Report - Attachments for 2001-2002
  - Duke Law School (2 of 3), 2002 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    Reports - There's a Chill in the Air: Fighting for Academic Freedom in Felten v. RIAA, Jennifer Westerhaus; Universal City Studios, Inc. v. Corley: The Constitutional Underpinnings of Fair Use Remain an Open Question (Fall 2001); Compulsory Licensing for AIDS Drugs under TRIPS: A Proposal for Expedited Review Process, Yoav Oestreicher; Memorandum on Circuit Precedent for Eldred First-Amendment Arguments; Standards "Review" of the Proposed "Common Control and Measurement Plane" (CCAMP) Protocol; Standards "Review" of the Proposed Multicast/Anycat Group Management (MAGMA) Protocol; An Analysis of Constitutional Issues Raised by Proposed Database Protection Legislation
  - Duke Law School (3 of 3), 2002 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    Server Liability Under the Proposed Notice and Statutory License Requirements for Digital Audio Transmissions, Matthew Greenley (April 14, 2002)
  - Fordham University, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    Media Diversity and Localism: Meaning, Metrics, and the Public Interest, Conference Report, December 15th and 16th, 2003
  - Fordham University, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    Grant No.: 10450187; Ford Foundation Grant Report - Media Diversity and Localism: Meaning, Metrics, and the Public Interest, Donald McGannon Communication Research Center, Philip M. Napoli; The Localism Principle in Communications Policymaking: An Annotated Bibliography (August 2004); Concentration, Content, Diversity, and Media Usage by Citizens/Consumers: An Annotated Bibliography; Working Paper - Market Structure, Station Ownership, and Local Public Affairs Programming on Local Broadcast Television; Working Paper - Reassessing Communications Research's Potential Contribution to Communications Policy: The Case of Media Ownership and the Diversity Index
  - Free Press, 2007 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    Pamphlets
  - Mobilizing Media Reform DVD, Presented by freepress, produced by KGHD Productions, 2007; DVD (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Fund for Constitutional Government, 1999-2001 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    Grant No.: 10000200 - correspondence, grant status report
  - Funding Exchange - Media Justice Fund, 2002-2004 (Box 5, Folder 30)
    Grant No.: 10300606 - pamphlets, reports, Annual Report on the Media Justice Fund of the Funding Exchange March 2003-2004; Strategic Grantmaking and Grassroots Organizing for Media Justice; Funding Exhange 2000-2001; Guide to Creative Giving; Grantmaking Docket Funding Exchange 2001-2002; Grantmaking Docket Funding Exchange 2002-2003
  - Future of Music Coalition, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 31)
    Grant No.: 10450348 - Future of Music Coalition: Capacity Building Grant Written Narrative and Financial and Financial Reports
  - Georgetown University, 2001-2005 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    Institute for Public Representation Georgetown University Law Center Washington, D.C. - Annual Report 2000-2001
  - Highlander Research and Education Center, 2002 (Box 5, Folder 33)
    Highlander Media Justice Gathering - Final Report, Prepared by Nan Rubin, September 2002
  - International Women's Tribune Centre, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 34)
    Grant No.: 10351882 - correspondence; Engendering Policy at the World Summit on the Information Society, Phase Two; pamphlets; A World Summit on the Information Society (WSIS) Report: Organizing for Social Justice and Human Rights in Global Media and Communications Policy; Gender Advocacy at the World Summit on the Information Society: Preliminary Observations, M. I. Franklin
  - Internews Network, 2001-2002 (Box 5, Folder 35)
    The Open Media Policy Initiative: A Proposal from Internews Network; pamphlets; and correspondence
  - Leadership Conference Education Fund (1 of 4), 2000-2001 (Box 6, Folder 36)
    Grant No.: 10000511 - correspondence and Leadership Conference Fund: Communications and Internet Policy Education and Community Outreach Initiative; The Leadership Conference on Civil Rights and The Leadership Conference Education Fund Building a Civil Rights E-Agenda for the 21st Century: "Expanding Digital Opportunity: The Debate over Funding for Education Technology" Speaker Series, April 5, 2001
  - Leadership Conference Education Fund (2 of 4), 2000-2001 (Box 6, Folder 37)
    Finding New Strategies to Achieve Media Diversity, July 26, 2001, National Education Association; Working Toward A Comprehensive Civil Rights E-Agenda, Communications and Internet Policy Wrap-Up 1999-2000; The Leadership Conference on Civil Rights and the Leadership Conference Education Fund "Building the Digital Bridge to the 21st Century: Broadband Deployment in Underserved Communities, May 21, 2001; The Leadership Conference on Civil Rights and the Leadership Conference Education Fund "Finding New Strategies to Achieve Media Diversity" July 26, 2001
  - Leadership Conference Education Fund (3 of 4), 2000-2001 (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - Leadership Conference Education Fund (4 of 4), 2001 (Box 6, Folder 39)
    Press release, correspondence, publication - From Digital Disconnect to Digital Empowerment: Building a More Equitable Society Through Leadership, Investment, and Collaboration
  - Link Media - WorldLink TV (1 of 2), 2000-2001 (Box 6, Folder 40)
    Grant No.: 10001087 - includes correspondence, grants reports, WorldLinkTV Business Plan (November 2001), pamphlets, and newsletters; Global Internet Policy Initiative (GIPI) documents
  - Link Media - WorldLink TV (2 of 2), 2001-2002 (Box 6, Folder 41)
    WorldLinkTV Reports
  - Media Access Project, 2004 (Box 7, Folder 42)
    Interim Report, September 2004
  - Media Channel, 2001-2002 (Box 7, Folder 43)
    Grant No.: 10002101 - Report on Grant Progress and a Proposal for Renewal from "The Media Channel" to Ford Foundation (February 2002)
  - National Congress of American Indians, 2002 (Box 7, Folder 44)
    Grant No.: 10251816 - Proposal to the Ford Foundation Media Policy and Technology Portfolio - Connecting Indian Country: Tribally-Driven Telecommunications Policy (June 2002)
  - Michigan State University, 2006 (Box 7, Folder 45)
    Making U.S. Telecommunications Policy: Who Participates and Who is Heard? The Roles of Research and Ideas, White Paper, Johannes M. Bauer, Sungjoong Kim, Steven S. Wildman
  - National Federation of Community Broadcasters (1 of 3), 2002 (Box 7, Folder 46)
    The 27th Annual Community Radio Conference (April 17-20, 2002); Assessment for NFCB Low Power Radio Project; newsletter; The Case for Free Air Time, Paul Taylor (March 2002)
  - National Federation of Community Broadcasters (2 of 3), 2003 (Box 7, Folder 47)
    Starting an LPFM Station, Kai Aiyetoro
  - National Federation of Community Broadcasters (3 of 3), 2003-2004 (Box 8, Folder 48)
    Newsletters; Media Policy Portfolio 2002 Interim Report, The National Federation of Community Broadcasters Making Low Power FM a Success (January 15, 2003); The 28th Annual Community Radio Conference, The National Youth in Radio Training Project, March 19-22, 2003 San Francisco; The 28th Annual Community Radio Conference, Attendee List (alphabetical), National Youth in Radio Training Project; The Ford Foundation Media Policy Portfolio 2002-2003 Final Report, The National Federation of Community Broadcasters Making a Low Power FM a Success (July 31, 2003); The 29th Annual Community Radio Conference, The 6th National Youth in Radio Training Project, April 20-24, 2004 Hyatt Regency Hotel, Albuquerque, NM
  - National Federation of Community Broadcasters (1 of 2), 2004 (Box 8, Folder 49)
    Correspondence; National Federation of Community Broadcasters Making a Low Power FM a Success 2004 Final Report; Newsletters; Community Radio News
  - National Federation of Community Broadcasters (2 of 2), 2004 (Box 8, Folder 50)
    KRBH-LP; KREV-LP; KRIM-LP; KRMN-LP; KSAP-LP; KSJC-LP; KURA-LP; KYGT-LP; KYRS-LP; WCEP-LP; WCNH-LP; WCOM-LP; KFCA-LP; WKUF-LP; WKVC-LP; WLLO-LP; WMRW-LP; WSHG-LP; WRFR-LP; WRYR-LP; WSBL-LP; WSCA-LP; WSWC-LP; WTJC-LP; WTND-LP; WXCS-LP
  - National Hispanic Media Coalition, 2004-2005 (Box 8, Folder 51)
    Proposal to the Ford Foundation for Support of the Development of the Latino Collaborative for Media Policy, Submitted by the National Hispanic Media Coalition (February 18, 2004); E-Newsletters; Correspondence
  - National Indian Telecommunications Institute, 2001 (Box 8, Folder 52)
    Report - Making Technology Our Own: Toward Technology Our Own, Practical Helps for Picking Phone and Internet Service in Indian Country, National Indian Telecommunications Institute; press materials; Information sheets
  - National Indian Telecommunications Institute CD, 2001; CD (Box 8, Folder 52)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. Access copy currently unavailable. Please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
  - New America Foundation (1 of 3), 2000 (Box 8, Folder 53)
    Grant No.: 10100245 - grant information files; correspondence; Common Wealth Program, Reclaiming the Electromagnetic Spectrum and Defending the Information Commons: A Proposal to the Ford Foundation (August 2000)
  - New America Foundation (2 of 3), 2001 (Box 9, Folder 54)
    Grant No.: 10100245 - Public Asset Program Interim Report (September 2001); correspondence; Working Paper - Battle Over the Airwaves: Principles for Spectrum Policy Reform, Michael Calabrese; Issue Brief - The Great Airwaves Robbery: The FCC's Decision on Channels 60-69 Could Transfer $10 Billion or More from Taxpayers to Broadcasters, Michael Calabrese; website printouts; press articles; Public Assets Program, Reclaiming the Electromagnetic Spectrum and Defending the Information Commons, A Proposal for Continued Support to the Ford Foundation (December 2001)
  - New American Foundation (3 of 3), 2002-2004 (Box 9, Folder 55)
    Grant Nos.: 10100245 and 10250971 - correspondence; Public Asset Program: Reclaiming the Electromagnetic Spectrum and Defending the Information Commons, Final Report (January 2002); news releases; Working Paper - The Myth of 'Free' TV, J.H. Snider; Working Paper - The Five Percent Solution: A Spectrum Fee to Replace the 'Public Interest Obligations' of Broadcasters, Henry Geller and Tim Watts; Working Paper - An Information Commons for E-Learning: Designing a Digital Opportunity Investment Trust, Thomas A. Kalil; Spectrum: Allocations, Auctions, Public Revenues Fact Sheet; press articles; The Cartoon Guide to Federal Spectrum Policy, J. H. Snider and Nigel Holmes
  - New Jersey Institute of Technology, 2002-2004 (Box 9, Folder 56)
    Community Informatics Systems (CIS): The Digital Revolution as an Enabler of Community Goals: A Proposal to the Ford Foundation Media Policy and Technology Program, Michael Gurstein; Toward a Citizen's Technology: Final Report to the Ford Foundation; On a Sector Analysis of the Community Informatics Systems Sector Draft
  - New York University, 2002-2003 (Box 9, Folder 57)
  - OMG Center for Collaborative Learning, 2002-2005 (Box 9, Folder 58)
    Proposal for Assessing and Advancing the Media Policy and Technology Field; Proposal Reflecting on and Learning from Stories from the Media Policy and Technology Field; The Makings of a Social Movement? Strategic Issues and Themes in Communications Policy Work: A Report from the Listening Project; pamphlets; publication - Design as a Catalyst for Learning; Summary Assessment Report - The Planning Phase of the Rebuilding Communities Initiative (July 1997); publication - Old Cities/Green Cities: Communities Transform Unmanaged Land
  - One Economy Corporation, 2001 (Box 9, Folder 59)
    Grant No.: 10101976; reports; Power, One Economy Corporation 2002 Annual Report
  - OneWorld International Foundation, 2001-2002 (Box 9, Folder 60)
    OneWorld U.S. Proposal to the Ford Foundation October 2001
  - Princeton University, 2000-2002 (Box 10, Folder 61)
    Grant No.: 10100409 - reports; correspondence; Serving the Public Interest in an Information Society: Proposal for an Undergraduate Internship Program
  - Prometheus Radio Project, 2000-2005 (Box 10, Folder 62)
    Grant No.: 10051067 - Prometheus Radio Project: A Project of Allston/Brighton Media Proposal Narrative; Grant Status Report; correspondence; Air Time for Democracy: A Proposal Submitted to the Ford Foundation by the Prometheus Radio Project (January 9, 2002); Prometheus Radio Project: Policy Program Reportback for 2004; press articles
  - Proteus Fund, 2005 (Box 10, Folder 63)
  - Public Knowledge (1 of 2), 2001-2004 (Box 10, Folder 64)
    Grant No.: 103003581 - Correspondence; reports; news articles; The Public's Stake in Intellectual Property Law: Developing the Missing Vocabulary: A Project Proposal for Public Knowledge; Annual Grant Report; What Every Citizen Should Know About DRM, a.k.a. "Digital Rights Management"
  - Public Knowledge (2 of 2), 2004-2005 (Box 10, Folder 65)
    Initial brief - American Library Association vs. Federal Communications Commission
  - Social Science Research Council (1 of 4), 2002 (Box 10, Folder 66)
    "Ownership, Stewardship, and Property in the Digital Age: Expanding the Conversation"; Rethinking the Voice of God: Constituting the Religious in Indigenous Media, Faye Ginsburg for Proceedings of December 2002 Conference on Religion and Media; Grant Report; Summer 2002 Institute: IT and Social Research: Setting the Agenda; correspondence; A Proposal for a Program of Research and Fellowships on 'Culture, Creativity, and Information Technology' (February 2002);; drafts; SSRC website printouts; Culture, Creativity and Information Technology - Planning grant proposal Draft (April 2002); Program on Information Technology, International Cooperation and Global Security (ITIC): Report on Progress of Research by ITIC Fellows 2001 Following Their Summer of Research; memos; Preposal: Program on Information Technology and International Cooperation (September 27, 2002); Social Research, Development, and the Internet: Fostering Online Social Science in Developing Societies (August 2002) (September 2002); Bridging the Socio-Technical Divide Draft 3 (November 2002); Project on Mapping Social Research on Information Technology draft (October 2002)
  - Social Science Research Council (2 of 4), 2003 (Box 10, Folder 67)
    Notes; correspondence; "Ownership, Stewardship and Property in a Digital Age: Expanding the Conversation"; Intellectual Property, Markets, and Cultural Flows" A Proposal for a Research Program at the Social Science Research Council Draft (December 2002); press articles; Alphabetical Files A-D
  - Social Science Research Council (3 of 4), 2003 (Box 11, Folder 68)
    Appropriating the Internet for Social Change: Towards the Strategic Use of Networked Technologies by Transnational Civil Society Organizations Verison 1.0 (November 2003)
  - Social Science Research Council (4 of 4), 2004 (Box 11, Folder 69)
    Correspondence; Intellectual Property, Markets, and Cultural Flows; Intellectual Property Rights: Challenges and Opportunities for the Ford Foundation, Joe Karaganis (October 2004); SSRC website printouts; Intellectual Property, Markets, and Cultural Flows: A Report and Agenda for Future Work - Final Grant Report for the Ford Foundation prepared by Joe Karaganis
  - Social Science Research Council, 2007 (Box 11, Folder 70)
    A Research Agenda for Media Policy in 2007: A Report on the Media Policy Research Pre-Conference, Memphis, TN, January 11, 2007; Necessary Knowledge for a Democratic Public Sphere - Current Research Studies; Toward a Federal Data Agenda for Communications Policymaking, Philip M. Napoli and Joe Karaganis; Federal Communications Law Journal - Necessary Knowledge for Communications Policy: Information Asymmetries and Commercial Data Access and Usage in the Policymaking Process (March 2007)
  - Southwest Missouri State University, 2004 (Box 11, Folder 71)
    Final Report on OurMedia/Nuestros Medios/NossaMidia IV, OURMedia.org, "Building Communications Societies", Porto Alegre, Brazil, July 22-25, 2004
  - Polymedia Manual - CD-R, 2004; CD-R (Box 11, Folder 71)
    Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
  - OM (OurMedia) Final Report - CD-R, 2004; CD-R (Box 11, Folder 71)
  - Stevens Institute of Technology, 2000-2001 (Box 11, Folder 72)
    Grant No.: 10150489 - correspondence; Reform of Telecommunications Taxes and Fees in New Jersey - A Research Study: Proposal Submitted to the Ford Foundation, M. Hosein Fallah, Thomas Lancaster, Nicholas Miller (October 2000); Reform of Telecommunications Taxes and Fees in New Jersey - A Research Study: Final Report (October 2001)
  - Syracuse University (1 of 2), 2001-2002 (Box 11, Folder 73)